A Guide to the Anthony-Seeger Campus School Records, 1956-1982: UA 0049
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Anthony-Seeger Campus School Records,
1956-1982
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Anthony-Seeger Campus School
Cooper, Ruth
Wampler, Marguerite, Dr., 1923-2013
UA 0049
1.682 cubic feet; 3 boxes
The Anthony-Seeger Campus School Records, 1956-1982, consist of three boxes containing administrative, historical, and personal materials relating to the school.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Kelly French, Dean's Office, College of Education, transferred three boxes of material related to the Anthony-Seeger Campus School (including handbooks, historical information, and administrative files) to Special Collections in October 1991 (AS 91-1016).
Provenance
Parent Teacher Association minutes and a set of scrapbooks kept by two teachers at Anthony-Seeger, housed in the Special Collections cage since 1982, were officially acquired and combined with aforementioned materials from the College of Education in March 1993 (AS 93-0303).
Appraisal Information
Upon receiving three boxes from the College of Education in 1991, library staff obtained permission to dispose of material as deemed proper. Per a note written by former librarian Chris Bolgiano and filed in the collection control file, staff reviewed the boxes in September 1992 and discarded various materials deemed non-archival, including invoices and receipts for daily supplies, monthly attendance records, preliminary inventory lists, faculty travel vouchers, blank forms of various kinds, menus, cafeteria purchase receipts, tally sheets for lunches served, and work-study pay period printouts.
Administrative History
The Anthony-Seeger Campus School was a combination nursery/K-6 elementary school (K-7 1965-1968) that operated on the JMU campus from 1958-1982. Named after two former directors of the Madison College teacher training program, Katherine M. Anthony (1885-1975) and Mary L. Seeger (1882-1975), and spearheaded by Harrisonburg Public Schools superintendent M. H. Bell and JMU's third president Dr. G. Tyler Miller (1902-1988), Anthony-Seeger acted as a lab for student teachers to learn the art of teaching, as well as a model school designed to offer a top-level educational experience for enrolled students. Attendance at the school was by application only, and enrollment vacillated between 200-400 students during the school's 24-year history. A significant portion of Anthony-Seeger students (e.g., 43.5% of K-6 students during the 1979-80 school year) were the children of university employees. Attendance for these students was free; all other students paid an annual tuition fee.
Starting in 1971, amid concerns over funding and the closure of other lab schools across the state, JMU's fourth president, Dr. Ronald E. Carrier (1932-2017), commissioned three studies to determine the efficacy of the Anthony-Seeger School and the practicability of its continued operation. The first study, commissioned in 1972, recommended the expansion of the school to include a learning diagnostic center for students with mental and physical disabilities. A subsequent study in 1979 raised the possibility of transferring operation of the school to Harrisonburg City Public Schools, or closing; neither option was pursued. A follow-up study in 1980 again considered closure, and again opted for continued operation, but in 1981, the school lost its bid for continued state funding and officially closed on June 4, 1982. In the years since, the Anthony-Seeger building has housed the local public radio station, WMRA; JMU's student-run radio station, WXJM; and JMU's newspaper, The Breeze (all now located off-campus). The building currently provides offices for the JMU police and the Center for Assessment and Research Studies.
Scope and Content
The Anthony-Seeger Campus School Records, 1956-1982, consist of administrative, historical, and personal materials related to the Anthony-Seeger Campus School. Materials include a variety of administrative files and items related to school history; graduation programs; Parent Teacher Association minutes; and two scrapbooks containing newspaper clippings, correspondence, photographs, and ephemera.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in 2 series:
Series 1: Administrative Files, 1958-1982
Series 2: Scrapbooks, 1956-1981
Each series is arranged chronologically. Exceptions to the chronological arrangement were made in order to pay respect to the original order, and to group like materials together.
Related Material
Anthony-Seeger Campus School Photographs, James Madison University Historic Photographs, 1919-ca. 2000, UA 0051, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University.
Bibliography
"Dr. G. Tyler Miller." FindaGrave, https://www.findagrave.com/memorial/104999977/g_-tyler-miller. Accessed September 23, 2019.
"Katherine Minor Anthony." FindaGrave, https://www.findagrave.com/memorial/66222075/katherine-minor-anthony. Accessed September 23, 2019.
"Dr. Marguerite Ausherman Long Wampler." FindaGrave, https://www.findagrave.com/memorial/105126774/marguerite-ausherman-wampler. Accessed September 23, 2019.
"Mary Louise Seeger." FindaGrave, https://www.findagrave.com/memorial/67132381/mary-louise-seeger. Accessed September 23, 2019.
"Dr. Ronald Edwin Carrier." Legacy, https://www.legacy.com/obituaries/name/dr-ronald-carrier-obituary?pid=186706544. Accessed September 23, 2019.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Madison College; James Madison University; Elementary schools -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg -- 20th century; Small schools -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg -- 20th century; Early childhood education; Education, Elementary; Harrisonburg (Va.) -- Education
Genre and Form Terms:
Scrapbooks; Administrative records; Minutes (administrative records); Photographs; Financial Records
- Series 1: Administrative Files, 1958-1982
  Scope and Content
  Series 1: Administrative Files, 1958-1982, consists of material relating to the history and everyday operation of the Campus School, including accreditation records (1978-1982), insurance information (1978-1981), and general PTA paperwork (1962-1974). Of special note is a Virginia Congress of Parents and Teachers year book from the 1971-1972 school year (does not include student information or photos), a 1981-1982 handbook, graduation programs from 1975-1982, a school history compiled by the last graduating sixth grade class in 1982, and a copy of the 1980 study commissioned by Dr. Carrier, which includes breakdowns of the student body by race and gender. Three folders contain PTA minutes ranging from 1958-1979, along with a few loose materials concerning the school's opening and closing.
  - PTA Minutes, 1958-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - PTA Minutes, 1962-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - PTA Minutes, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - PTA (General), 1962-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Yearbook/Handbook, 1971-1972, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Attendance Reports, 1975-1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Graduation Programs, 1975-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Insurance, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Inventory, 1978-1981 (Box OV 2, Folder 5)
  - Accreditation, 1978-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Financial Records, 1979-1980 (Box OV 2, Folder 6)
  - Accounting, 1980-1981 (Box OV 2, Folder 7)
  - Study/School History, 1980, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Budget, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series 2: Scrapbooks, 1956-1981
  Series 2: Scrapbooks, 1956-1981, consists of two sets of scrapbooks maintained by teachers at Anthony-Seeger. The first, compiled by second grade teacher Ruth Cooper, covers her tenure at the school (1958-1973); the second, maintained by fourth grade teacher Dr. Marguerite Wampler (1923-2013), covers the years 1973-1979. Both sets of scrapbooks include newspaper clippings, correspondence, programs, photographs, and ephemera related to the school's history. Of special note is a copy of the letter sent by Superintendent Bell to parents in 1956, alerting them to the school's imminent opening; photos of Cooper's second grade class watching the construction of an addition to the Anthony-Seeger building; and multiple articles on Anthony and Seeger, including their obituaries.
  - Ruth Cooper Scrapbook, 1956-1960 (Box OV 1, Folder 1)
  - Ruth Cooper Scrapbook, 1960-1966 (Box OV 1, Folder 2)
  - Ruth Cooper Scrapbook, 1966-1971 (Box OV 1, Folder 3)
  - Ruth Cooper Scrapbook, 1971-1973 (Box OV 2, Folder 1)
  - Marguerite Wampler Scrapbook, 1973-1975 (Box OV 2, Folder 2)
  - Marguerite Wampler Scrapbook, 1975-1977 (Box OV 2, Folder 3)
  - Marguerite Wampler Scrapbook, 1977-1979 (Box OV 2, Folder 4)
  - Loose Material from Scrapbooks, 1967-1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)